<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    

    <title>DERAILED WEB</title>
    <generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
		<icon>http://opreaadrian.github.io/apple-touch-icon-precomposed.png</icon>
    <subtitle>Opinionated blog about JavaScript, life, and everything inbetween.</subtitle>
    <link href="http://opreaadrian.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://opreaadrian.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T02:14:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://opreaadrian.github.io/</id>
    <author>
			<name>Adrian Oprea</name>
			<uri>http://opreaadrian.github.io/</uri>
			
		</author>

    
    <entry>
        <title>Worldwide Meteor Day in Bucharest</title>
        <link href="http://opreaadrian.github.io/javascript/meteor/meteor-day-bucharest/"/>
        <updated>2014-11-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
        <id>http://opreaadrian.github.io/javascript/meteor/meteor-day-bucharest</id>
        <author>
					<name>Adrian Oprea</name>
					<uri>http://opreaadrian.github.io/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;My story with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meteor.com/&quot;&gt;Meteor&lt;/a&gt; started about 5 months ago, when I accidentally stumbled upon some tweets about this awesome, reactive-style platform, that allows you to prototype and build state of the art web applications, in really short timespans. I saved those tweets , and when I had some spare time, later that day, I dug deeper, fiddled with a few sample apps,and what I found was amazing — a platform that allows you to prototype, build, refine, and deploy real-time web applications (really mean concurrency and real-time here), at a high pace, AND IT HAS CLIENT-SIDE DB for rapid prototyping.
One month later, I quit my job and got hired as a web developer in a company that was actually planning on rewriting one of their core applications with Meteor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward, 5 months later, I attended the first official MeteorJS meetup organized in Bucharest, on November 06th. It so happened that on that day, the “meteorites” celebrate the Worldwide Meteor Day, so this was a good opportunity to meet enthusiasts, view some app demos, and discuss the reasons why people actually use, in their day-to-day work Meteor, instead of other solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evening started with a short networking session, where we got to meet each other, see what areas of expertise are involved, and get a general feel of the crowd. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, I met people coming from various fields, ranging from ex marketing experts, former sysadmins, open-source volunteers/committers and hardcore e-commerce solution architects, to front-end developers looking to delve deeper into backend development.
When I asked how they got into Meteor, the majority of them replied that they were sold to the fact that they can have that level of responsiveness in one bottle. Given the fact that not all of them had the technical background that we are used to, CS degree, 10+ years in software development and the like, the ease with which Meteor apps can be developed really got them going, as generally speaking, realtime applications are not that easy to code, and a lot of thought needs to be put into choosing the right tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this short networking session, we got down to the good stuff, which was the presentation of the new Meteor tutorial, we got our hands dirty with a real Meteor application, and we all got the chance to test the application and see the way it responds, when dealing with multiple users. I know that this probably does not sound fantastic, but it is, given the fact that it ran off the presenter’s machine, and not some fancy AWS instance with unlimited resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the sample application presentation was done, some of the guys presented their own applications, and gave a brief presentation of the tools they’ve used, time it took them to prototype/build the applications and the trouble they faced. 
I found one of the applications to be particularly interesting, especially because we are in the process of electing a new president, and this guy’s application was presenting all the presidency candidates, and you were able to choose who you wanted to vote with — I know that the vote is secret, but this allows you to show your support for a particular candidate.
In case you are interested about the application, it is called “Votez Pe” — I’m voting for — and you can find it at &lt;a href=&quot;https://votez.pe&quot;&gt;votez.pe&lt;/a&gt;. The code is on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ciocan/votez.pe&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; so if you feel like fiddling with it, then go ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, the best was saved for last, so in the last part of our meeting, we got online with other people that were celebrating Meteor Day throughout Europe, and we also had the chance to talk to an actual MeteorJS representative, and ask him some questions, concerning the direction that the platform is taking. The questions revolved around the subject of commercial version vs. community version, debugging tools, problems that people are facing when developing with Meteor and the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guy, who’s name I actually forgot, to my disgrace, was actually a new employee, but he said that before getting hired at Meteor, he actually did a lot of blog posts on the subject, and he seemed to have all the information under his belt, so he was able to answer all our questions in a very swift and polite manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After wrapping up our Q&amp;amp;A session, we had a short chat, agreed that this community needs to be taken care of, maintained, and hopefully, sooner than we expect, our own company will host a MeteorJS meetup and maybe we’ll have even more people joining, and presenting their apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as a closing thought, I was impressed in a very pleasant way, and I am really happy that I attended &lt;a href=&quot;http://meteorday.com/&quot;&gt;Worldwide Meteor Day&lt;/a&gt;. I will try to encourage, participate, and support these types of events going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Thoughts on Angular 2.0</title>
        <link href="http://opreaadrian.github.io/javascript/thoughts-on-angular-2.0/"/>
        <updated>2014-11-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
        <id>http://opreaadrian.github.io/javascript/thoughts-on-angular-2.0</id>
        <author>
					<name>Adrian Oprea</name>
					<uri>http://opreaadrian.github.io/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;Today I just started officially blogging, and I feel like a bit of a punk, starting my so-called blogging career with something that resembles a diss, but, Google, you just ruined HTML with your Angular 2.0 plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a big fan of Angular, and I really love the way it behaves, and how performant it can be when used right, but when I wanted to find out more about the plans Google has with Angular 2.0, it kind of threw me back… way back. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently working on a side project that is a little bit of a mess right now. Built on Django, with JavaScript mixed in Jinja templates(and the other way around), all scripts dumped in the HTML, RequireJS on top of everything, and some libraries that I never heard of, built by weird russian guys(fantastic backend devs) — no pun intended — the project rings the average developer’s “LET’S REWRITE THIS SHIT” bell. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After countless discussions with my client, he finally agreed to have his backend developer build a RESTful API for me to use with … you guessed it, folks, the new Angular app that I was planning on building for him. 
I actually thought Angular would be the greatest solution and I based my choice on the following facts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Angular is maintained by Google.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is mature enough in the web development landscape.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has a huge comunity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After making this choice, I already created a basic structure for the app, and laid out the bricks that form the base of the app — folder structure, module hierarchy, initial markup, tools setup, tests, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the fact that now I have to re-evaluate the framework landscape and think of another framework I can use for my client, the biggest reason I’m so upset with this change has more of a historical nuance. 
If you remember the way Microsoft tried to have/push their own JavaScript, in IE — see &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JScript&quot;&gt;JScript&lt;/a&gt; — then you can probably see the same thing done by Google nowadays. There have been a lot of attempts like this, and to some degree, they feel like a normal thing to me, as the bigger companies would like to have it their way, but none struck me so hard, as I was not that involved in development and nor did I care about standards so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it just feels like Google wants to have their own WorldWideWeb, with this way of writing Angular apps, and by imposing such a specific way of writing apps, the developped, the so-called “Angular developer” who knows very little about JavaScript, but can talk for days about &lt;code&gt;$scope&lt;/code&gt;, two-way data binding, and how they’re the most awesome things in the Universe after &lt;code&gt;42&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to summarize my complaint, and also to illustrate why I’m feeling Angular 2.0 syntax is wrong, take a look:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;!-- The Angular 1.3 way --&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;button ng-click=&quot;deleteTodo(todo)&quot;&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;!-- The Angular 1.3 way with valid HTML --&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;button data-ng-click=&quot;deleteTodo(todo)&quot;&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;!-- Angular 2.0 way --&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;button (click)=&quot;deleteTodo(todo)&quot;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since when is &lt;code&gt;(click)&lt;/code&gt; an HTML attribute? Google, you’re making HTML &lt;em&gt;too declarative&lt;/em&gt; as far as I’m concerned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to debate all the modifications that feel wrong to me, so as a closing thought, I’d like to encourage you to talk and share your thoughts in the comments section.&lt;/p&gt;


        </content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>